# Curriculum Vitae: Chad McKell

## **ABOUT**

updated: 9/24

Position Research Scientist

Company Meta, Reality Labs Research (via Sigma Connectivity)

Address 10301 Willows Road NE, Redmond, WA 98052

Phone +1 661 289 4215 Email cmckell@meta.com Website chadmckell.com

Research My research spans mathematical modeling and numerical simulation of physical systems

with an emphasis on acoustics and audio. I am especially interested in applications of acoustic wave simulation in audio technology and auditory biophysics. Current projects include geometric boundary modeling for wave simulation; non-spherical harmonics for sound simulation and capture; and variational principles for elastic wave simulation. Past projects include underwater acoustic sensing and optical standing-wave trapping.

## **EDUCATION**

9/19-	University of California San Diego, Ph.D. in Computer Music
	Dissertation: Geometric Boundary Modeling for Wave Simulation.
	Advisors: Albert Chern (Computer Science) and Miller Puckette (Music).
9/16-10/17	University of Edinburgh, M.S. in Acoustics and Music Technology
8/09-12/15	Wake Forest University, M.S. in Physics
6/02-8/09	Brigham Young University, B.S. in Biophysics

## **EMPLOYMENT**

9/24-	Meta, Reality Labs Research (via Sigma Connectivity), Research Scientist
3/24-6/24	University of California San Diego, Teaching Assistant in Computer Science
6/23-2/24	Meta, Reality Labs Research, Research Scientist Intern
8/21-3/22	Meta, Reality Labs Research, Research Intern
9/19-6/23	University of California San Diego, Teaching Assistant/Researcher in Music
7/18-7/19	Applied Research in Acoustics, R&D Scientist
5/18-5/18	Moog Music, Freelance Audio Software Developer
4/17-9/17	Lofelt (acquired by Meta in 2022), Freelance Acoustics Researcher
10/14-8/16	J.P. Morgan/Neovest (via ConsultNet), Software Development Engineer in Test
8/12-12/12	University of North Carolina School of the Arts, Adjunct Instructor of Physics
9/09-9/11	Wake Forest University, Teaching Assistant in Physics
9/08-6/09	Brigham Young University, Tutorial Lab Assistant in Physics
8/07-3/09	Brigham Young University, Research Assistant in Philosophy

## RESEARCH ACTIVITIES

9/24— Meta, Reality Labs Research (via Sigma Connectivity), Research Scientist

Redmond, Washington. Research topics: computational physics, numerical simulation, parallel computing. Research summary: Build multiphysics models and custom high-performance acoustic wave simulation software for applications in virtual and augmented reality. Supervisor: Sebastian Prepeliță. Team Lead: Ravish Mehra (Research Audio). I work for Meta as a vendor employed full-time by Sigma Connectivity.

#### RESEARCH ACTIVITIES CONT.

## 9/19- University of California San Diego, Ph.D. Student

La Jolla, California. Research topics: computational physics, numerical simulation, differential geometry. Dissertation summary: developed mathematical and computational methods for handling geometric boundaries in wave simulations. Committee members: Albert Chern (co-chair), Miller Puckette (co-chair), Melvin Leok, Shahrokh Yadegari, Stefan Bilbao (Univ. of Edinburgh), and Sebastian Prepeliță (Meta).

## 6/23-2/24 Meta, Reality Labs Research, Research Scientist Intern

Redmond, Washington. Research topics: computational acoustics, numerical simulation, parallel computing. Research summary: Built custom high-performance acoustic wave simulation software for applications in virtual and augmented reality. Supervisor: Sebastian Prepeliță. Team Lead: Ravish Mehra (Research Audio).

## 8/21-3/22 Meta, Reality Labs Research, Research Intern

La Jolla, California. Research description: see above.

## 7/18–7/19 Applied Research in Acoustics, R&D Scientist

Culpeper, Virginia. Research topics: underwater acoustic sensing, acoustic beamforming. Research summary: developed physics-based signal processing algorithms for object detection and classification in naval sonar systems. Team Lead: Jonathan Botts.

## 1/17–8/17 University of Edinburgh, Master's Student

Edinburgh, Scotland. Research topics: computational acoustics, elastodynamics, numerical simulation. Research summary: developed numerical simulations of structural acoustic vibrations for commercial haptic devices. My thesis was partially funded by Lofelt, a Berlin-based haptic feedback company acquired by Meta in 2022. Advisor: Stefan Bilbao.

## 1/10–9/13 Wake Forest University, Master's Student

Winston-Salem, North Carolina. Research topics: optical trapping, laser beam characterization, fluid dynamics. Research summary: simulated and fabricated standing-wave optical traps for Brownian particle tracking. Advisor: Keith Bonin.

### 8/07-8/09 Brigham Young University, Undergraduate Student

Provo, Utah. Research topics: structural biology, scanning probe microscopy. Research summary: investigated the physical effect of anesthetics on lipid bilayer structures using atomic force microscopy. Advisor: David Busath.

### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

## As Instructor

U	IN	$\mathbf{C}$	$\mathbf{S}$	A

SCI 1100 General Physics. Fall 2012 (1 term).

## As TA

$\underline{ ext{UCSD}}$	
CSE 291	Physics Simulation. Spring 2024 (1 term).
MUS 5	Sound in Time. Spring 2020 (1 term).
MUS 6	Electronic Music. Fall 2020 (1 term).
MUS 15	Popular Music: David Bowie. Winter 2021 (1 term).
MUS 15	Popular Music: Video Game Music. Winter 2020 (1 term).

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE CONT.

MUS 171	Computer Music I. Winter 2022 (1 term).	
MUS 172	Computer Music II. 2021–2022 (2 terms).	
<u><b>WFU</b></u> PHY 113 PHY 114	General Physics I (Mechanics). 2009–2011 (4 terms). General Physics II (E&M). Fall 2010 (1 term).	

## As Tutor

$\underline{\mathbf{BYU}}$	
PHSCS 105	General Physics 1 (Mechanics). 2008–2009 (2 terms).
PHSCS 106	General Physics 2 (E&M). Winter 2009 (1 term).
PHSCS 121	Principles of Physics 1 (Mechanics). 2008–2009 (2 terms).
PHSCS 123	Principles of Physics 2 (Waves/Thermo). W/Sp 2009 (2 terms).
PHSCS 220	Principles of Physics 3 (E&M). W/Sp 2009 (2 terms)

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

### Manuscripts in Progress

(1) C. McKell, M. Nabizadeh, S. Wang, and A. Chern, "Wave simulations in infinite spacetime".

Simulating wave propagation on an infinite domain has been a long-standing computational challenge. Conventional approaches to this problem only produce wave simulations on a small subset of the infinite domain. Using the fact that wave propagation on an infinite Minkowski spacetime is equivalent to wave propagation on a bounded Minkowski spacetime under a Kelvin-like transformation, we simulate wave propagation on the entire infinite domain using a finite discretization of the bounded domain with no additional loss of accuracy from the transformation.

(2) C. McKell, Geometric Boundary Modeling for Wave Simulation, Ph.D. Dissertation, University of California San Diego. Defense planned for Fall 2024. Advisors: Albert Chern and Miller Puckette.

This work presents novel geometric methods for handling open exterior boundaries in wave simulations. First, I discuss extensions to the reflectionless discrete perfectly matched layer for the wave and Helmholtz equations. Then, I demonstrate that the conformal invariance of the wave equation under a Kelvin transform in Minkowski spacetime allows one to convert an infinite domain problem into a bounded domain problem that can be solved using standard numerical methods with no additional loss of accuracy introduced by the transform. I conclude by discussing parallel computing strategies for the geometric boundary models, applications in architectural acoustics and binaural audio, and future work in obstacle boundary flattening.

### **Journal Articles**

(3) C. McKell and K. Bonin, "Optical corral using a standing-wave Bessel beam," *Journal of the Optical Society of America B*, Vol. 35, No. 8, 1910–1920, 2018.

### PUBLICATIONS CONT.

## Conference Proceedings

(4) C. McKell, "Sonification of optically-ordered Brownian motion," In Proceedings of the International Computer Music Conference (ICMC), Utrecht, Netherlands, September 2016.

## Master's Theses

- (5) C. McKell, Real-Time Physical Modeling for Haptic Feedback Rendering, Master's Thesis, University of Edinburgh, Acoustics and Audio Group, 2017. Advisor: Stefan Bilbao.
- (6) C. McKell, Confinement and Tracking of Brownian Particles in a Bessel Beam Standing Wave, Master's Thesis, Wake Forest University, Department of Physics, 2015. Advisor: Keith Bonin.

## **Technical Reports**

(7) C. McKell, H. Conley, and D. Busath, "AFM study of structural changes in supported planar DPPC bilayers containing general anesthetic isoflurane," Brigham Young University, Paper 827, 2010.